<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="authentication-common-auth-services">
  <title>Common Authentication Services</title>

  <sect1 id="mechanisms-providers-entry-points">
    <title>Mechanisms, Providers and Entry Points</title>

    <para>If you're using Spring Security-provided authentication
    approaches, you'll usually need to configure a web filter, together
    with an <literal>AuthenticationProvider</literal> and
    <literal>AuthenticationEntryPoint</literal>. In this section we are
    going to explore an example application that needs to support both
    form-based authentication (ie so a nice HTML page is presented to a
    user for them to login) plus BASIC authentication (ie so a web service
    or similar can access protected resources).</para>

    <para>In the web.xml, this application will need a single Acegi
    Security filter in order to use the FilterChainProxy. Nearly every
    Spring Security application will have such an entry, and it looks like
    this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;filter&gt;
&lt;filter-name&gt;Spring Security Filter Chain Proxy&lt;/filter-name&gt;
&lt;filter-class&gt;org.springframework.security.util.FilterToBeanProxy&lt;/filter-class&gt;
&lt;init-param&gt;
&lt;param-name&gt;targetClass&lt;/param-name&gt;
&lt;param-value&gt;org.springframework.security.util.FilterChainProxy&lt;/param-value&gt;
&lt;/init-param&gt;
&lt;/filter&gt;

&lt;filter-mapping&gt;
&lt;filter-name&gt;Spring Security Filter Chain Proxy&lt;/filter-name&gt;
&lt;url-pattern&gt;/*&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
&lt;/filter-mapping&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>The above declarations will cause every web request to be passed
    through to Spring Security's FilterChainProxy. As explained in the
    filters section of this reference guide, the
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> is a generally-useful class
    that enables web requests to be passed to different filters based on
    the URL patterns. Those delegated filters are managed inside the
    application context, so they can benefit from dependency injection.
    Let's have a look at what the FilterChainProxy bean definition would
    look like inside your application context:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="filterChainProxy"
        class="org.springframework.security.util.FilterChainProxy"&gt;
&lt;property name="filterInvocationDefinitionSource"&gt;
&lt;value&gt;
  CONVERT_URL_TO_LOWERCASE_BEFORE_COMPARISON
  PATTERN_TYPE_APACHE_ANT
  /**=httpSessionContextIntegrationFilter,logoutFilter,authenticationProcessingFilter,basicProcessingFilter,securityContextHolderAwareRequestFilter,rememberMeProcessingFilter,anonymousProcessingFilter,exceptionTranslationFilter,filterInvocationInterceptor,switchUserProcessingFilter
&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>Internally Spring Security will use a
    <literal>PropertyEditor</literal> to convert the string presented in
    the above XML fragment into a
    <literal>FilterInvocationDefinitionSource</literal> object. What's
    important to note at this stage is that a series of filters will be
    run - in the order specified by the declaration - and each of those
    filters are actually the <literal>&lt;bean id&gt;</literal> of another
    bean inside the application context. So, in our case some extra beans
    will also appear in the application context, and they'll be named
    <literal>httpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</literal>,
    <literal>logoutFilter</literal> and so on. The order that the filters
    should appear is discussed in the filters section of the reference
    guide - although they are correct in the above example.</para>

    <para>In our example we have the
    <literal>AuthenticationProcessingFilter</literal> and
    <literal>BasicProcessingFilter</literal> being used. These are the
    "authentication mechanisms" that respond to form-based authentication
    and BASIC HTTP header-based authentication respectively (we discussed
    the role of authentication mechanisms earlier in this reference
    guide). If you weren't using form or BASIC authentication, neither of
    these beans would be defined. You'd instead define filters applicable
    to your desired authentication environment, such as
    <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> or
    <literal>CasProcessingFilter</literal>. Refer to the individual
    chapters of this part of the reference guide to learn how to configure
    each of these authentication mechanisms.</para>

    <para>Recall that
    <literal>HttpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</literal> keeps the
    contents of the <literal>SecurityContext</literal> between invocations
    inside an HTTP session. This means the authentication mechanisms are
    only used once, being when the principal initially tries to
    authenticate. The rest of the time the authentication mechanisms sit
    there and silently pass the request through to the next filter in the
    chain. That is a practical requirement due to the fact that few
    authentication approaches present credentials on each and every call
    (BASIC authentication being a notable exception), but what happens if
    a principal's account gets cancelled or disabled or otherwise changed
    (eg an increase or decrease in <literal>GrantedAuthority[]</literal>s)
    after the initial authentication step? Let's look at how that is
    handled now.</para>

    <para>The major authorization provider for secure objects has
    previously been introduced as
    <literal>AbstractSecurityInterceptor</literal>. This class needs to
    have access to an <literal>AuthenticationManager</literal>. It also
    has configurable settings to indicate whether an
    <literal>Authentication</literal> object should be re-authenticated on
    each secure object invocation. By default it just accepts any
    <literal>Authentication</literal> inside the
    <literal>SecurityContextHolder</literal> is authenticated if
    <literal>Authentication.isAuthenticated()</literal> returns true. This
    is great for performance, but not ideal if you want to ensure
    up-to-the-moment authentication validity. For such cases you'll
    probably want to set the
    <literal>AbstractSecurityInterceptor.alwaysReauthenticate</literal>
    property to true.</para>

    <para>You might be asking yourself, "what's this
    <literal>AuthenticationManager</literal>?". We haven't explored it
    before, but we have discussed the concept of an
    <literal>AuthenticationProvider</literal>. Quite simply, an
    <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename> is responsible
    for passing requests through a chain of AuthenticationProviders. It's
    a little like the filter chain we discussed earlier, although there
    are some differences. There is only one
    <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename> implementation
    shipped with Spring Security, so let's look at how it's configured for
    the example we're using in this chapter:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="authenticationManager"
        class="org.springframework.security.providers.ProviderManager"&gt;
&lt;property name="providers"&gt;
&lt;list&gt;
  &lt;ref local="daoAuthenticationProvider"/&gt;
  &lt;ref local="anonymousAuthenticationProvider"/&gt;
  &lt;ref local="rememberMeAuthenticationProvider"/&gt;
&lt;/list&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>It's probably worth mentioning at this point that your
    authentication mechanisms (which are usually filters) are also
    injected with a reference to the
    <literal>AuthenticationManager</literal>. So both
    <literal>AbstractSecurityInterceptor</literal> as well as the
    authentication mechanisms will use the above
    <literal>ProviderManager</literal> to poll a list of
    <literal>AuthenticationProvider</literal>s.</para>

    <para>In our example we have three providers. They are tried in the
    order shown (which is implied by the use of a <literal>List</literal>
    instead of a <literal>Set</literal>), with each provider able to
    attempt authentication, or skip authentication by simply returning
    <literal>null</literal>. If all implementations return null, the
    <literal>ProviderManager</literal> will throw a suitable exception. If
    you're interested in learning more about chaining providers, please
    refer to the <literal>ProviderManager</literal> JavaDocs.</para>

    <para>The providers to use will sometimes be interchangeable with the
    authentication mechanisms, whilst at other times they will depend on a
    specific authentication mechanism. For example, the
    <literal>DaoAuthenticationProvider</literal> just needs a string-based
    username and password. Various authentication mechanisms result in the
    collection of a string-based username and password, including (but not
    limited to) BASIC and form authentication. Equally, some
    authentication mechanisms create an authentication request object
    which can only be interpreted by a single type of
    <literal>AuthenticationProvider</literal>. An example of this
    one-to-one mapping would be JA-SIG CAS, which uses the notion of a
    service ticket which can therefore only be authenticated by
    <literal>CasAuthenticationProvider</literal>. A further example of a
    one-to-one mapping would be the LDAP authentication mechanism, which
    can only be processed an the
    <literal>LdapAuthenticationProvider</literal>. The specifics of such
    relationships are detailed in the JavaDocs for each class, plus the
    authentication approach-specific chapters of this reference guide. You
    need not be terribly concerned about this implementation detail,
    because if you forget to register a suitable provider, you'll simply
    receive a <literal>ProviderNotFoundException</literal> when an attempt
    to authenticate is made.</para>

    <para>After configuring the correct authentication mechanisms in the
    <literal>FilterChainProxy</literal>, and ensuring that a corresponding
    <literal>AuthenticationProvider</literal> is registered in the
    <literal>ProviderManager</literal>, your last step is to configure an
    <literal>AuthenticationEntryPoint</literal>. Recall that earlier we
    discussed the role of <literal>ExceptionTranslationFilter</literal>,
    which is used when HTTP-based requests should receive back an HTTP
    header or HTTP redirect in order to start authentication. Continuing
    on with our earlier example:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="exceptionTranslationFilter"
        class="org.springframework.security.ui.ExceptionTranslationFilter"&gt;
&lt;property name="authenticationEntryPoint"&gt;&lt;ref local="authenticationProcessingFilterEntryPoint"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="accessDeniedHandler"&gt;
&lt;bean class="org.springframework.security.ui.AccessDeniedHandlerImpl"&gt;
  &lt;property name="errorPage" value="/accessDenied.jsp"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="authenticationProcessingFilterEntryPoint"
        class="org.springframework.security.ui.webapp.AuthenticationProcessingFilterEntryPoint"&gt;
&lt;property name="loginFormUrl"&gt;&lt;value&gt;/acegilogin.jsp&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="forceHttps"&gt;&lt;value&gt;false&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>Notice that the <literal>ExceptionTranslationFilter</literal>
    requires two collaborators. The first,
    <literal>AccessDeniedHandlerImpl</literal>, uses a
    <literal>RequestDispatcher</literal> forward to display the specified
    access denied error page. We use a forward so that the
    <literal>SecurityContextHolder</literal> still contains details of the
    principal, which may be useful for display to the user (in old
    releases of Spring Security we relied upon the servlet container to
    handle a 403 error message, which lacked this useful contextual
    information). <literal>AccessDeniedHandlerImpl</literal> will also set
    the HTTP header to 403, which is the official error code to indicate
    access denied. In the case of the
    <literal>AuthentionEntryPoint</literal>, here we're setting what
    action we would like taken when an unauthenticated principal attempts
    to perform a protected operation. Because in our example we're going
    to be using form-based authentication, we specify
    <literal>AuthenticationProcessinFilterEntryPoint</literal> and the URL
    of the login page. Your application will usually only have one entry
    point, and most authentication approaches define their own specific
    <literal>AuthenticationEntryPoint</literal>. Details of which entry
    point to use for each authentication approach is discussed in the
    authentication approach-specific chapters of this reference
    guide.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="userdetails-and-associated-types">
    <title>UserDetails and Associated Types</title>

    <para>As mentioned in the first part of the reference guide, most
    authentication providers take advantage of the
    <literal>UserDetails</literal> and
    <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> interfaces. The contract for
    this latter interface consists of a single method:</para>

    <para><programlisting>public UserDetails loadUserByUsername(String username) throws UsernameNotFoundException, DataAccessException;</programlisting></para>

    <para>The returned <literal>UserDetails</literal> is an interface that
    provides getters that guarantee non-null provision of basic
    authentication information such as the username, password, granted
    authorities and whether the user is enabled or disabled. Most
    authentication providers will use a
    <literal>UserDetailsService</literal>, even if the username and
    password are not actually used as part of the authentication decision.
    Generally such provider will be using the returned
    <literal>UserDetails</literal> object just for its
    <literal>GrantedAuthority[]</literal> information, because some other
    system (like LDAP or X509 or CAS etc) has undertaken the
    responsibility of actually validating the credentials.</para>

    <para>A single concrete implementation of
    <literal>UserDetails</literal> is provided with Spring Security, being
    the <literal>User</literal> class. Spring Security users will need to
    decide when writing their <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> what
    concrete <literal>UserDetails</literal> class to return. In most cases
    <literal>User</literal> will be used directly or subclassed, although
    special circumstances (such as object relational mappers) may require
    users to write their own <literal>UserDetails</literal> implementation
    from scratch. This is not such an unusual situation, and users should
    not hesitate to simply return their normal domain object that
    represents a user of the system. This is especially common given that
    <literal>UserDetails</literal> is often used to store additional
    principal-related properties (such as their telephone number and email
    address), so that they can be easily used by web views.</para>

    <para>Given <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> is so simple to
    implement, it should be easy for users to retrieve authentication
    information using a persistence strategy of their choice. Having said
    that, Spring Security does include a couple of useful base
    implementations, which we'll look at below.</para>

    <sect2 id="in-memory-service">
      <title>In-Memory Authentication</title>

      <para>Whilst it is easy to use create a custom
      <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> implementation that extracts
      information from a persistence engine of choice, many applications
      do not require such complexity. This is particularly true if you're
      undertaking a rapid prototype or just starting integrating Spring
      Security, when you don't really want to spend time configuring
      databases or writing <literal>UserDetailsService</literal>
      implementations. For this sort of situation, a simple option is to
      configure the <literal>InMemoryDaoImpl</literal>
      implementation:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="inMemoryDaoImpl"
          class="org.springframework.security.userdetails.memory.InMemoryDaoImpl"&gt;
&lt;property name="userMap"&gt;
&lt;value&gt;
  rod=koala,ROLE_TELLER,ROLE_SUPERVISOR
  dianne=emu,ROLE_TELLER
  scott=wombat,ROLE_TELLER
  peter=opal,disabled,ROLE_TELLER
&lt;/value&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;        </programlisting></para>

      <para>In the above example, the <literal>userMap</literal> property
      contains each of the usernames, passwords, a list of granted
      authorities and an optional enabled/disabled keyword. Commas are
      used to delimit each token. The username must appear to the left of
      the equals sign, and the password must be the first token to the
      right of the equals sign. The <literal>enabled</literal> and
      <literal>disabled</literal> keywords (case insensitive) may appear
      in the second or any subsequent token. Any remaining tokens are
      treated as granted authorities, which are created as
      <literal>GrantedAuthorityImpl</literal> objects (this is just for
      your reference - most applications don't need custom
      <literal>GrantedAuthority</literal> implementations, so using the
      default implementation in this manner is just fine). Note that if a
      user has no password and/or no granted authorities, the user will
      not be created in the in-memory authentication repository.</para>

      <para><literal>InMemoryDaoImpl</literal> also offers a
      <literal>setUserProperties(Properties)</literal> method, which
      allows you to externalise the
      <literal>java.util.Properties</literal> in another Spring configured
      bean or an external properties file. You might like to use Spring's
      <literal>PropertiesFactoryBean</literal>, which is useful for
      loading such external properties files. This setter might prove
      useful for simple applications that have a larger number of users,
      or deployment-time configuration changes, but do not wish to use a
      full database for handling authentication details.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-service">
      <title>JDBC Authentication</title>

      <para>Spring Security also includes a
      <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> that can obtain authentication
      information from a JDBC data source. Internally Spring JDBC is used,
      so it avoids the complexity of a fully-featured object relational
      mapper (ORM) just to store user details. If your application does
      use an ORM tool, you might prefer to write a custom
      <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> to reuse the mapping files
      you've probably already created. Returning to
      <literal>JdbcDaoImpl</literal>, an example configuration is shown
      below:</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="dataSource" class="org.springframework.jdbc.datasource.DriverManagerDataSource"&gt;
&lt;property name="driverClassName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="url"&gt;&lt;value&gt;jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://localhost:9001&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="username"&gt;&lt;value&gt;sa&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="password"&gt;&lt;value&gt;&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="jdbcDaoImpl" class="org.springframework.security.userdetails.jdbc.JdbcDaoImpl"&gt;
&lt;property name="dataSource"&gt;&lt;ref bean="dataSource"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;        </programlisting></para>

      <para>You can use different relational database management systems
      by modifying the <literal>DriverManagerDataSource</literal> shown
      above. You can also use a global data source obtained from JNDI, as
      per normal Spring options. Irrespective of the database used and how
      a <literal>DataSource</literal> is obtained, a standard schema must
      be used as indicated in <literal>dbinit.txt</literal>. You can
      download this file from the Spring Security web site.</para>

      <para>If your default schema is unsuitable for your needs,
      <literal>JdbcDaoImpl</literal> provides two properties that allow
      customisation of the SQL statements. You may also subclass the
      <literal>JdbcDaoImpl</literal> if further customisation is
      necessary. Please refer to the JavaDocs for details, although please
      note that the class is not intended for complex custom subclasses.
      If you have complex needs (such as a special schema or would like a
      certain <literal>UserDetails</literal> implementation returned),
      you'd be better off writing your own
      <literal>UserDetailsService</literal>. The base implementation
      provided with Spring Security is intended for typical situations,
      and does not offer infinite configuration flexibility.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="concurrent-sessions">
    <title>Concurrent Session Handling</title>

    <para>Spring Security is able to prevent a principal from concurrently
    authenticating to the same application more than a specified number of
    times. Many ISVs take advantage of this to enforce licensing, whilst
    network administrators like this feature because it helps prevent
    people from sharing login names. You can, for example, stop user
    "Batman" from logging onto the web application from two different
    sessions.</para>

    <para>To use concurrent session support, you'll need to add the
    following to <literal>web.xml</literal>:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;listener&gt;
&lt;listener-class&gt;org.springframework.security.ui.session.HttpSessionEventPublisher&lt;/listener-class&gt;
&lt;/listener&gt;        </programlisting></para>

    <para>In addition, you will need to add the
    <literal>org.springframework.security.concurrent.ConcurrentSessionFilter</literal>
    to your <literal>FilterChainProxy</literal>. The
    <classname>ConcurrentSessionFilter</classname> requires two
    properties, <literal>sessionRegistry</literal>, which generally points
    to an instance of <literal>SessionRegistryImpl</literal>, and
    <literal>expiredUrl</literal>, which points to the page to display
    when a session has expired.</para>

    <para>The <literal>web.xml</literal>
    <literal>HttpSessionEventPublisher</literal> causes an
    <literal>ApplicationEvent</literal> to be published to the Spring
    <literal>ApplicationContext</literal> every time a
    <literal>HttpSession</literal> commences or terminates. This is
    critical, as it allows the <literal>SessionRegistryImpl</literal> to
    be notified when a session ends.</para>

    <para>You will also need to wire up the
    <literal>ConcurrentSessionControllerImpl</literal> and refer to it
    from your <literal>ProviderManager</literal> bean:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;bean id="authenticationManager"
        class="org.springframework.security.providers.ProviderManager"&gt;
&lt;property name="providers"&gt;
&lt;!-- your providers go here --&gt;
&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="sessionController"&gt;&lt;ref bean="concurrentSessionController"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="concurrentSessionController"
        class="org.springframework.security.concurrent.ConcurrentSessionControllerImpl"&gt;
&lt;property name="maximumSessions"&gt;&lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;property name="sessionRegistry"&gt;&lt;ref local="sessionRegistry"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="sessionRegistry" class="org.springframework.security.concurrent.SessionRegistryImpl"/&gt;</programlisting></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="authentication-taglibs">
    <title>Authentication Tag Libraries</title>

    <para><literal>AuthenticationTag</literal> is used to simply output a
    property of the current principal's
    <literal>Authentication.getPrincipal()</literal> object to the web
    page.</para>

    <para>The following JSP fragment illustrates how to use the
    <literal>AuthenticationTag</literal>:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;security:authentication operation="username"/&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>This tag would cause the principal's name to be output. Here we
    are assuming the <literal>Authentication.getPrincipal()</literal> is a
    <literal>UserDetails</literal> object, which is generally the case
    when using the typical
    <literal>DaoAuthenticationProvider</literal>.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
