<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="community">
<title>Community Support</title>

<sect1 id="jira">
    <title>Use JIRA for Issue Tracking</title>
    
    <para>Spring Security uses JIRA to manage bug reports and enhancement
        requests. If you find a bug, please log a report using JIRA. Do not
        log it on the support forum, mailing list or by emailing the project's
        developers. Such approaches are ad-hoc and we prefer to manage bugs
        using a more formal process.</para>
    
    <para>If possible, in your JIRA report please provide a JUnit test
        that demonstrates any incorrect behaviour. Or, better yet, provide a
        patch that corrects the issue. Similarly, enhancements are welcome to
        be logged in JIRA, although we only accept commit enhancement requests
        if you include corresponding unit tests. This is necessary to ensure
        project test coverage is adequately maintained.</para>
    
    <para>You can access JIRA at <ulink
        url="http://opensource.atlassian.com/projects/spring/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10040"></ulink>.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="becoming-involved">
    <title>Becoming Involved</title>
    
    <para>We welcome you to become involved in Spring Security project.
        There are many ways of contributing, including reading the mailing
        list and responding to questions from other people, writing new code,
        improving existing code, assisting with documentation, developing
        samples or tutorials, or simply making suggestions.</para>
    
    <para>Please read our project policies web page that is available on
        Spring Security home page. This explains the path to become a
        committer, and the administration approaches we use within the
        project.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="further-info">
    <title>Further Information</title>
    
    <para>Questions and comments on Spring Security are welcome. Please
        use the Spring Community Forum web site at <ulink
            url="http://forum.springframework.org"></ulink> for all support
        issues. Remember to use JIRA for bug reports, as explained above.
        Everyone is also welcome to join the Acegisecurity-developer mailing
        list and participate in design discussions. It's also a good way of
        finding out what's happening with regard to release timing, and the
        traffic volume is quite light. Finally, our project home page (where
        you can obtain the latest release of the project and convenient links
        to Subversion, JIRA, mailing lists, forums etc) is at <ulink
            url="http://acegisecurity.org"></ulink>.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>