<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">                         

<chapter id="digest">
    <title>Digest Authentication</title>
    
    <sect1 id="digest-overview">
        <title>Overview</title>
        
        <para>Spring Security provides a
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> which is capable of
            processing digest authentication credentials presented in HTTP
            headers. Digest Authentication attempts to solve many of the
            weaknesses of Basic authentication, specifically by ensuring
            credentials are never sent in clear text across the wire. Many user
            agents support Digest Authentication, including FireFox and Internet
            Explorer. The standard governing HTTP Digest Authentication is defined
            by RFC 2617, which updates an earlier version of the Digest
            Authentication standard prescribed by RFC 2069. Most user agents
            implement RFC 2617. Spring Security
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> is compatible with the
            "<literal>auth</literal>" quality of protection
            (<literal>qop</literal>) prescribed by RFC 2617, which also provides
            backward compatibility with RFC 2069. Digest Authentication is a
            highly attractive option if you need to use unencrypted HTTP (ie no
            TLS/HTTPS) and wish to maximise security of the authentication
            process. Indeed Digest Authentication is a mandatory requirement for
            the WebDAV protocol, as noted by RFC 2518 Section 17.1, so we should
            expect to see it increasingly deployed and replacing Basic
            Authentication.</para>
        
        <para>Digest Authentication is definitely the most secure choice
            between Form Authentication, Basic Authentication and Digest
            Authentication, although extra security also means more complex user
            agent implementations. Central to Digest Authentication is a "nonce".
            This is a value the server generates. Spring Security's nonce adopts
            the following format:</para>
        
        <para><programlisting>base64(expirationTime + ":" + md5Hex(expirationTime + ":" + key))
            
            expirationTime:   The date and time when the nonce expires, expressed in milliseconds
            key:              A private key to prevent modification of the nonce token
        </programlisting></para>
        
        <para>The <literal>DigestProcessingFilterEntryPoint</literal> has a
            property specifying the <literal>key</literal> used for generating the
            nonce tokens, along with a <literal>nonceValiditySeconds</literal>
            property for determining the expiration time (default 300, which
            equals five minutes). Whist ever the nonce is valid, the digest is
            computed by concatenating various strings including the username,
            password, nonce, URI being requested, a client-generated nonce (merely
            a random value which the user agent generates each request), the realm
            name etc, then performing an MD5 hash. Both the server and user agent
            perform this digest computation, resulting in different hash codes if
            they disagree on an included value (eg password). In Spring Security
            implementation, if the server-generated nonce has merely expired (but
            the digest was otherwise valid), the
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilterEntryPoint</literal> will send a
            <literal>"stale=true"</literal> header. This tells the user agent
            there is no need to disturb the user (as the password and username etc
            is correct), but simply to try again using a new nonce.</para>
        
        <para>An appropriate value for
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilterEntryPoint</literal>'s
            <literal>nonceValiditySeconds</literal> parameter will depend on your
            application. Extremely secure applications should note that an
            intercepted authentication header can be used to impersonate the
            principal until the <literal>expirationTime</literal> contained in the
            nonce is reached. This is the key principle when selecting an
            appropriate setting, but it would be unusual for immensely secure
            applications to not be running over TLS/HTTPS in the first
            instance.</para>
        
        <para>Because of the more complex implementation of Digest
            Authentication, there are often user agent issues. For example,
            Internet Explorer fails to present an "<literal>opaque</literal>"
            token on subsequent requests in the same session. Spring Security
            filters therefore encapsulate all state information into the
            "<literal>nonce</literal>" token instead. In our testing, Spring
            Security implementation works reliably with FireFox and Internet
            Explorer, correctly handling nonce timeouts etc.</para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="digest-config">
        <title>Configuration</title>
        
        <para>Now that we've reviewed the theory, let's see how to use it. To
            implement HTTP Digest Authentication, it is necessary to define
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> in the fitler chain. The
            application context will need to define the
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> and its required
            collaborators:</para>
        
        <para><programlisting>
            &lt;bean id="digestProcessingFilter" class="org.springframework.security.ui.digestauth.DigestProcessingFilter"&gt;
            &lt;property name="userDetailsService"&gt;&lt;ref local="jdbcDaoImpl"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;property name="authenticationEntryPoint"&gt;&lt;ref local="digestProcessingFilterEntryPoint"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;property name="userCache"&gt;&lt;ref local="userCache"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;/bean&gt;
            
            &lt;bean id="digestProcessingFilterEntryPoint"
            class="org.springframework.security.ui.digestauth.DigestProcessingFilterEntryPoint"&gt;
            &lt;property name="realmName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;Contacts Realm via Digest Authentication&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;property name="key"&gt;&lt;value&gt;acegi&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;property name="nonceValiditySeconds"&gt;&lt;value&gt;10&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
            &lt;/bean&gt;
            
        </programlisting></para>
        
        <para>The configured <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> is needed
            because <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> must have direct
            access to the clear text password of a user. Digest Authentication
            will NOT work if you are using encoded passwords in your DAO. The DAO
            collaborator, along with the <literal>UserCache</literal>, are
            typically shared directly with a
            <literal>DaoAuthenticationProvider</literal>. The
            <literal>authenticationEntryPoint</literal> property must be
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilterEntryPoint</literal>, so that
            <literal>DigestProcessingFilter</literal> can obtain the correct
            <literal>realmName</literal> and <literal>key</literal> for digest
            calculations.</para>
        
        <para>Like <literal>BasicAuthenticationFilter</literal>, if
            authentication is successful an <literal>Authentication</literal>
            request token will be placed into the
            <literal>SecurityContextHolder</literal>. If the authentication event
            was successful, or authentication was not attempted because the HTTP
            header did not contain a Digest Authentication request, the filter
            chain will continue as normal. The only time the filter chain will be
            interrupted is if authentication fails and the
            <literal>AuthenticationEntryPoint</literal> is called, as discussed in
            the previous paragraph.</para>
        
        <para>Digest Authentication's RFC offers a range of additional
            features to further increase security. For example, the nonce can be
            changed on every request. Despite this, Spring Security implementation
            was designed to minimise the complexity of the implementation (and the
            doubtless user agent incompatibilities that would emerge), and avoid
            needing to store server-side state. You are invited to review RFC 2617
            if you wish to explore these features in more detail. As far as we are
            aware, Spring Security's implementation does comply with the minimum
            standards of this RFC.</para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>