<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                         "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="sample-apps">
<title id="samples">Sample Applications</title>

<sect1 id="contacts-sample">
    <title id="contacts">Contacts</title>
    
    <para>Included with Spring Security is a very simple application that
        can demonstrate the basic security facilities provided by the system
        (and confirm your Container Adapter is properly configured if you're
        using one).</para>
    
    <para>If you build from Subversion, the Contacts sample application
        includes three deployable versions:
        <literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-filter.war</literal> is
        configured with the HTTP Session Authentication approach.
        <literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-ca.war</literal> is
        configured to use a Container Adapter. Finally,
        <literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-cas.war</literal> is designed
        to work with a JA-SIG CAS server. If you're just wanting to see how
        the sample application works, please use
        <literal><literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-filter.war</literal></literal>
        as it does not require special configuration of your container. This
        is also the artifact included in official release ZIPs.</para>
    
    <para>To deploy, simply copy the relevant WAR file from Spring
        Security distribution into your container’s <literal>webapps</literal>
        directory.</para>
    
    <para>After starting your container, check the application can load.
        Visit
        <literal>http://localhost:8080/spring-security-sample-contacts-filter</literal>
        (or whichever URL is appropriate for your web container and the WAR
        you deployed). A random contact should be displayed. Click "Refresh"
        several times and you will see different contacts. The business method
        that provides this random contact is not secured.</para>
    
    <para>Next, click "Debug". You will be prompted to authenticate, and a
        series of usernames and passwords are suggested on that page. Simply
        authenticate with any of these and view the resulting page. It should
        contain a success message similar to the following:</para>
    
    <blockquote>
        <para>Context on SecurityContextHolder is of type:
            org.springframework.security.context.SecurityContextImpl</para>
        
        <para>The Context implements SecurityContext.</para>
        
        <para>Authentication object is of type:
            org.springframework.security.adapters.PrincipalSpringSecurityUserToken</para>
        
        <para>Authentication object as a String:
            org.springframework.security.adapters.PrincipalSpringSecurityUserToken@e9a7c2:
            Username: rod; Password: [PROTECTED]; Authenticated: true; Granted
            Authorities: ROLE_TELLER, ROLE_SUPERVISOR</para>
        
        <para>Authentication object holds the following granted
            authorities:</para>
        
        <para>ROLE_TELLER (getAuthority(): ROLE_TELLER)</para>
        
        <para>ROLE_SUPERVISOR (getAuthority(): ROLE_SUPERVISOR)</para>
        
        <para>SUCCESS! Your [container adapter|web filter] appears to be
            properly configured!</para>
    </blockquote>
    
    <para>If you receive a different message, and deployed
        <literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-ca.war</literal>, check you
        have properly configured your Container Adapter as described elsewhere
        in this reference guide.</para>
    
    <para>Once you successfully receive the above message, return to the
        sample application's home page and click "Manage". You can then try
        out the application. Notice that only the contacts available to the
        currently logged on user are displayed, and only users with
        <literal>ROLE_SUPERVISOR</literal> are granted access to delete their
        contacts. Behind the scenes, the
        <literal>MethodSecurityInterceptor</literal> is securing the business
        objects. If you're using or
        <literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-cas.war</literal>, the
        <literal><literal>spring-security-sample-contacts-filter.war</literal></literal>
        <literal>FilterSecurityInterceptor</literal> is also securing the HTTP
        requests. If using either of these WARs, be sure to try visiting
        <literal>http://localhost:8080/contacts/secure/super</literal>, which
        will demonstrate access being denied by the
        <literal>FilterSecurityInterceptor</literal>. Note the sample
        application enables you to modify the access control lists associated
        with different contacts. Be sure to give this a try and understand how
        it works by reviewing the sample application's application context XML
        files.</para>
    
    <para>The Contacts sample application also include a
        <literal>client</literal> directory. Inside you will find a small
        application that queries the backend business objects using several
        web services protocols. This demonstrates how to use Spring Security
        for authentication with Spring remoting protocols. To try this client,
        ensure your servlet container is still running the Contacts sample
        application, and then execute <literal>client rod koala</literal>. The
        command-line parameters respectively represent the username to use,
        and the password to use. Note that you may need to edit
        <literal>client.properties</literal> to use a different target
        URL.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="tutorial-sample">
    <title>Tutorial Sample</title>
    
    <para>Whilst the <link linkend="contacts-sample">Contacts
        Sample</link> is quite advanced in that it illustrates the more
        powerful features of domain object access control lists and so on,
        sometimes you just want to start with a nice basic example. The
        tutorial sample is intended to provide this for you.</para>
    
    <para>The compiled tutorial is included in the distribution ZIP file,
        ready to be deployed into your web container. Authentication is
        handled by the <link linkend="dao-provider">DaoAuthenticationProvider</link>, using the
        <link linkend="in-memory-service">in-memory</link>
        <literal>UserDetailsService</literal> that sources information from
        the <literal>users.properties</literal> file located in the WAR's
        <literal>/WEB-INF</literal> directory. The <link linkend="form">form-based</link> 
        authentication mechanism is used, with the commonly-used 
        <link linkend="remember-me">remember-me</link>
        authentication provider used to automatically remember the login using
        cookies.</para>
    
    <para>In terms of authorization, to keep things simple we've
        configured the tutorial to only perform some basic <link
            linkend="filter-invocation-authorization">web filter
            authorization</link>. We've wired two common <link
                linkend="pre-invocation">pre-invocation access decision voters</link>,
        being the <literal>RoleVoter</literal> and
        <literal>AuthenticatedVoter</literal>, such that
        <literal>ROLE_*</literal> configuration attributes and
        <literal>IS_AUTHENTICATED_*</literal> configuration attributes may be
        used. Of course, it's extremely easy to add in other providers, with
        most users probably starting with some services-layer security using
        <link linkend="aop-alliance">MethodSecurityInterceptor</link>.</para>
    
    <para>We recommend you start with the tutorial sample, as the XML is
        minimal and easy to follow. All of the needed <link
            linkend="filters">filters</link> are configured properly, and using
        best practise. Most importantly, you can easily this one XML file (and
        its corresponding <literal>web.xml</literal> entries) to your existing
        application. Only when this basic integration is achieved do we
        suggest you attempt adding in method authorization or domain object
        security.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>