<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="supporting-infrastructure" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  
  <info><title>Supporting Infrastructure</title></info>
  

  <para>This chapter introduces some of the supplementary and supporting
  infrastructure used by Spring Security. If a capability is not directly
  related to security, yet included in the Spring Security project, we
  will discuss it in this chapter.</para>

  <section xml:id="localization">
    <title>Localization</title>
    <para>Spring Security supports localization of exception messages that
    end users are likely to see. If your application is designed for
    English users, you don't need to do anything as by default all
    Security Security messages are in English. If you need to support
    other locales, everything you need to know is contained in this
    section.</para>

    <para>All exception messages can be localized, including messages
    related to authentication failures and access being denied
    (authorization failures). Exceptions and logging that is focused on
    developers or system deployers (including incorrect attributes,
    interface contract violations, using incorrect constructors, startup
    time validation, debug-level logging) etc are not localized and
    instead are hard-coded in English within Spring Security's
    code.</para>

    <para>Shipping in the <literal>spring-security-core-xx.jar</literal> you
    will find an <literal>org.springframework.security</literal> package
    that in turn contains a <literal>messages.properties</literal> file.
    This should be referred to by your
    <literal>ApplicationContext</literal>, as Spring Security classes
    implement Spring's <literal>MessageSourceAware</literal> interface and
    expect the message resolver to be dependency injected at application
    context startup time. Usually all you need to do is register a bean
    inside your application context to refer to the messages. An example
    is shown below:</para>

    <para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="messageSource" class="org.springframework.context.support.ReloadableResourceBundleMessageSource">
  <property name="basename" value="org/springframework/security/messages"/>
</bean>
]]></programlisting></para>

    <para>The <literal>messages.properties</literal> is named in
    accordance with standard resource bundles and represents the default
    language supported by Spring Security messages. This default file is
    in English. If you do not register a message source, Spring Security
    will still work correctly and fallback to hard-coded English versions
    of the messages.</para>

    <para>If you wish to customize the
    <literal>messages.properties</literal> file, or support other
    languages, you should copy the file, rename it accordingly, and
    register it inside the above bean definition. There are not a large
    number of message keys inside this file, so localization should not be
    considered a major initiative. If you do perform localization of this
    file, please consider sharing your work with the community by logging
    a JIRA task and attaching your appropriately-named localized version
    of <literal>messages.properties</literal>.</para>

    <para>Rounding out the discussion on localization is the Spring
    <literal>ThreadLocal</literal> known as
    <literal>org.springframework.context.i18n.LocaleContextHolder</literal>.
    You should set the <literal>LocaleContextHolder</literal> to represent
    the preferred <literal>Locale</literal> of each user. Spring Security
    will attempt to locate a message from the message source using the
    <literal>Locale</literal> obtained from this
    <literal>ThreadLocal</literal>. Please refer to Spring documentation
    for further details on using <literal>LocaleContextHolder</literal>
    and the helper classes that can automatically set it for you (eg
    <literal>AcceptHeaderLocaleResolver</literal>,
    <literal>CookieLocaleResolver</literal>,
    <literal>FixedLocaleResolver</literal>,
    <literal>SessionLocaleResolver</literal> etc)</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="filters">
    <info><title>Filters</title></info>

    <para>Spring Security uses many filters, as referred to throughout the
      remainder of this reference guide. If you are using <link xlink:href="#ns-config">namespace configuration</link>,
      then the you don't usually have to declare the filter beans explicitly. There may be times when you want full control
      over the security filter chain, either because you are using features which aren't supported in the namespace, or you
      are using your own customized versions of classes.</para>
    <para>In this case, you have a choice in how these filters are added to your web application, in that you can use either
        Spring's <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> or 
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname>. We'll look at both below.</para>
      
    <para>When using <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal>, you will see
      something like this in the web.xml file:
      
        <programlisting>
    &lt;filter&gt;
        &lt;filter-name&gt;myFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
        &lt;filter-class&gt;org.springframework.web.filter.DelegatingFilterProxy&lt;/filter-class&gt;
    &lt;/filter&gt;

    &lt;filter-mapping&gt;
      &lt;filter-name&gt;myFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
      &lt;url-pattern&gt;/*&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/filter-mapping&gt;
        </programlisting>     
       
        Notice that the filter  is actually a <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal>, 
        and not the filter that will actually implement the logic of the filter. What
        <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> does is delegate the
    <literal>Filter</literal>'s methods through to a bean which is
    obtained from the Spring application context. This enables the bean to
    benefit from the Spring web application context lifecycle support and
    configuration flexibility. The bean must implement
    <literal>javax.servlet.Filter</literal> and it must have the same name as that in
        the <literal>filter-name</literal> element.</para>

    <para>There is a lifecycle issue to consider when hosting
    <literal>Filter</literal>s in an IoC container instead of a servlet
    container. Specifically, which container should be responsible for
    calling the <literal>Filter</literal>'s "startup" and "shutdown"
    methods? It is noted that the order of initialization and destruction
    of a <literal>Filter</literal> can vary by servlet container, and this
    can cause problems if one <literal>Filter</literal> depends on
    configuration settings established by an earlier initialized
    <literal>Filter</literal>. The Spring IoC container on the other hand
    has more comprehensive lifecycle/IoC interfaces (such as
    <literal>InitializingBean</literal>,
    <literal>DisposableBean</literal>, <literal>BeanNameAware</literal>,
    <literal>ApplicationContextAware</literal> and many others) as well as
    a well-understood interface contract, predictable method invocation
    ordering, autowiring support, and even options to avoid implementing
    Spring interfaces (eg the <literal>destroy-method</literal> attribute
    in Spring XML). For this reason we recommend the use of Spring
    lifecycle services instead of servlet container lifecycle services
    wherever possible. Read the Javadoc for <classname>DelegatingFilterProxy</classname>
    for more information</para>

      <para>Rather than using <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal>, we
    strongly recommend that you use <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> instead.
          Whilst <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> is a very useful class,
    the problem is that the number of lines of code required for
    <literal>&lt;filter&gt;</literal> and
    <literal>&lt;filter-mapping&gt;</literal> entries in
    <literal>web.xml</literal> explodes when using more than a few
    filters. To overcome this issue, Spring Security provides a
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> class. It is wired using a
          <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> (just like in the example above),
    but the target class is
    <literal>org.springframework.security.util.FilterChainProxy</literal>.
    The filter chain is then declared in the application context, using
    code such as this:</para>

    <para><programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="filterChainProxy" class="org.springframework.security.util.FilterChainProxy">
  <sec:filter-chain-map path-type="ant">
     <sec:filter-chain pattern="/webServices/**" 
         filters="httpSessionContextIntegrationFilterWithASCFalse,basicProcessingFilter,exceptionTranslationFilter,filterSecurityInterceptor"/>
     <sec:filter-chain pattern="/**" 
         filters="httpSessionContextIntegrationFilterWithASCTrue,authenticationProcessingFilter,exceptionTranslationFilter,filterSecurityInterceptor"/>
  </sec:filter-chain-map>
</bean>
]]>         
    </programlisting></para>

    <para>You may notice similarities with the way
    <classname>FilterSecurityInterceptor</classname> is declared. Both regular
    expressions and Ant Paths are supported, and the most specific URIs
    appear first. At runtime the <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> will
    locate the first URI pattern that matches the current web request and the list
    of filter beans specified by the <literal>filters</literal> attribute
    will be applied to that request. The filters will be invoked in the order
    they are defined, so you have complete control over the filter chain
    which is applied to a particular URL.</para>

    <para>You may have noticed we have declared two
    <classname>HttpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</classname>s in the filter
    chain (<literal>ASC</literal> is short for
    <literal>allowSessionCreation</literal>, a property of
    <classname>HttpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</classname>). As web
    services will never present a <literal>jsessionid</literal> on future
    requests, creating <literal>HttpSession</literal>s for such user
    agents would be wasteful. If you had a high-volume application which
    required maximum scalability, we recommend you use the approach shown
    above. For smaller applications, using a single
    <classname>HttpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</classname> (with its
    default <literal>allowSessionCreation</literal> as
    <literal>true</literal>) would likely be sufficient.</para>

    <para>In relation to lifecycle issues, the
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> will always delegate
    <literal>init(FilterConfig)</literal> and <literal>destroy()</literal>
    methods through to the underlaying <literal>Filter</literal>s if such
    methods are called against <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> itself.
    In this case, <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> guarantees to only
    initialize and destroy each <literal>Filter</literal> once,
    irrespective of how many times it is declared by the
    <interfacename>FilterInvocationDefinitionSource</interfacename>. You control the
    overall choice as to whether these methods are called or not via the
        <literal>targetFilterLifecycle</literal> initialization parameter of the
        <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> that proxies
        <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal>. As discussed above, by default
    any servlet container lifecycle invocations are not delegated through
    to <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal>.</para>

    <para>You can use the attribute <literal>filters = "none"</literal>
      in the same way that you do when using <link xlink:href="#namespace-auto-config">namespace configuration</link>
      to build the <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname>. This will omit the
      request pattern from the security filter chain entirely.
       Note that anything matching this path will then have
    no authentication or authorization services applied and will be freely
    accessible.</para>

    <para>The order that filters are defined in <literal>web.xml</literal>
    is very important. Irrespective of which filters you are actually
    using, the order of the <literal>&lt;filter-mapping&gt;</literal>s
    should be as follows:</para>

    <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>ChannelProcessingFilter</literal>, because it might
        need to redirect to a different protocol</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><literal>ConcurrentSessionFilter</literal>, because it
        doesn't use any <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname>
        functionality but needs to update the
        <interfacename>SessionRegistry</interfacename> to reflect ongoing requests
        from the principal</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><classname>HttpSessionContextIntegrationFilter</classname>, so a
        <interfacename>SecurityContext</interfacename> can be setup in the
        <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname> at the beginning of a web
        request, and any changes to the <interfacename>SecurityContext</interfacename>
        can be copied to the <literal>HttpSession</literal> when the web
        request ends (ready for use with the next web request)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Authentication processing mechanisms -
        <literal>AuthenticationProcessingFilter</literal>,
        <literal>CasProcessingFilter</literal>,
        <literal>BasicProcessingFilter, HttpRequestIntegrationFilter,
        JbossIntegrationFilter</literal> etc - so that the
        <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname> can be modified to
        contain a valid <interfacename>Authentication</interfacename> request
        token</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The
        <literal>SecurityContextHolderAwareRequestFilter</literal>, if you
        are using it to install a Spring Security aware
        <literal>HttpServletRequestWrapper</literal> into your servlet
        container</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><classname>RememberMeProcessingFilter</classname>, so that if no
        earlier authentication processing mechanism updated the
        <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname>, and the request presents
        a cookie that enables remember-me services to take place, a
        suitable remembered
        <interfacename>Authentication</interfacename> object will
        be put there</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><literal>AnonymousProcessingFilter</literal>, so that if no
        earlier authentication processing mechanism updated the
        <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname>, an anonymous
        <interfacename>Authentication</interfacename> object will be put there</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><classname>ExceptionTranslationFilter</classname>, to catch any
        Spring Security exceptions so that either an HTTP error response
        can be returned or an appropriate
        <interfacename>AuthenticationEntryPoint</interfacename> can be launched</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><classname>FilterSecurityInterceptor</classname>, to protect web
        URIs</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>All of the above filters use
    <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> or
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname>. It is recommended that a single
        <literal>DelegatingFilterProxy</literal> proxy through to a single
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> for each application, with that
    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> defining all of Spring Security
    filters.</para>

    <para>If you're using SiteMesh, ensure Spring Security filters execute
    before the SiteMesh filters are called. This enables the
    <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname> to be populated in time for
    use by SiteMesh decorators</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="taglib">
    <info><title>Tag Libraries</title></info> 

    <para>Spring Security comes bundled with several JSP tag libraries which provide a range of different
      services.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="taglib-config">
      <info><title>Configuration</title></info>
      <para>All taglib classes are included in the core
        <literal>spring-security-xx.jar</literal> file, with the
        <literal>security.tld</literal> located in the JAR's
        <literal>META-INF</literal> directory. This means for JSP 1.2+ web
        containers you can simply include the JAR in the WAR's
        <literal>WEB-INF/lib</literal> directory and it will be available. If
        you're using a JSP 1.1 container, you'll need to declare the JSP
        taglib in your <literal>web.xml file</literal>, and include
        <literal>security.tld</literal> in the <literal>WEB-INF/lib</literal>
        directory. The following fragment is added to
        <literal>web.xml</literal>:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<taglib>
  <taglib-uri>http://www.springframework.org/security/tags</taglib-uri> 
  <taglib-location>/WEB-INF/security.tld</taglib-location>
</taglib>
]]></programlisting></para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="taglib-usage">
      <info><title>Usage</title></info>
      <para>Now that you've configured the tag libraries, refer to the
        individual reference guide sections for details on how to use them.
        Note that when using the tags, you should include the taglib reference
        in your JSP: 
<programlisting>
  &lt;%@ taglib prefix='security' uri='http://www.springframework.org/security/tags' %&gt;
          
        </programlisting></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>