<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="community"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>Spring Security Community</title>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="jira">
        <info>
            <title>Issue Tracking</title>
        </info>
        <para>Spring Security uses JIRA to manage bug reports and enhancement requests. If you find
            a bug, please log a report using JIRA. Do not log it on the support forum, mailing list
            or by emailing the project's developers. Such approaches are ad-hoc and we prefer to
            manage bugs using a more formal process.</para>
        <para>If possible, in your issue report please provide a JUnit test that demonstrates any
            incorrect behaviour. Or, better yet, provide a patch that corrects the issue. Similarly,
            enhancements are welcome to be logged in the issue tracker, although we only accept
            enhancement requests if you include corresponding unit tests. This is necessary to
            ensure project test coverage is adequately maintained.</para>
        <para>You can access the issue tracker at <link
            xlink:href="http://jira.springsource.org/browse/SEC"
            >http://jira.springsource.org/browse/SEC</link>. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="becoming-involved">
        <info>
            <title>Becoming Involved</title>
        </info>
        <para>We welcome your involvement in the Spring Security project. There are many ways of
            contributing, including reading the forum and responding to questions from other people,
            writing new code, improving existing code, assisting with documentation, developing
            samples or tutorials, or simply making suggestions.</para>
        <!-- TODO: Not currently there on SSec 2.0
    <para>Please read our project policies web page that is available on
        Spring Security home page. This explains the path to become a
        committer, and the administration approaches we use within the
        project.</para>

        -->
    </section>
    <section xml:id="further-info">
        <info>
            <title>Further Information</title>
        </info>
        <para>Questions and comments on Spring Security are welcome. You can use the Spring
            Community Forum web site at <uri xlink:href="http://forum.springsource.org"
            >http://forum.springsource.org</uri> to discuss Spring Security with other users of the
            framework. Remember to use JIRA for bug reports, as explained above.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
