<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="ns-config"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <info>
        <title>Security Namespace Configuration</title>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para> Namespace configuration has been available since version 2.0 of the Spring framework.
            It allows you to supplement the traditional Spring beans application context syntax with
            elements from additional XML schema. You can find more information in the Spring <link
            xlink:href="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/htmlsingle/spring-framework-reference.html"
            > Reference Documentation</link>. A namespace element can be used simply to allow a more
            concise way of configuring an individual bean or, more powerfully, to define an
            alternative configuration syntax which more closely matches the problem domain and hides
            the underlying complexity from the user. A simple element may conceal the fact that
            multiple beans and processing steps are being added to the application context. For
            example, adding the following element from the security namespace to an application
            context will start up an embedded LDAP server for testing use within the application: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <security:ldap-server />
]]></programlisting> This is much simpler than wiring up the equivalent Apache Directory Server
            beans. The most common alternative configuration requirements are supported by
            attributes on the <literal>ldap-server</literal> element and the user is isolated from
            worrying about which beans they need to create and what the bean property names are. <footnote>
            <para>You can find out more about the use of the <literal>ldap-server</literal> element
                in the chapter on <link xlink:href="#ldap">LDAP</link>.</para>
            </footnote>. Use of a good XML editor while editing the application context file should
            provide information on the attributes and elements that are available. We would
            recommend that you try out the <link
            xlink:href="http://www.springsource.com/products/sts">SpringSource Tool Suite</link> as
            it has special features for working with standard Spring namespaces. </para>
        <para> To start using the security namespace in your application context, you need to have
            the <literal>spring-security-config</literal> jar on your classpath. Then all you need
            to do is add the schema declaration to your application context file: <programlisting language="xml">
  <![CDATA[
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
  xmlns:security="http://www.springframework.org/schema/security"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
          http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd
          http://www.springframework.org/schema/security
          http://www.springframework.org/schema/security/spring-security.xsd">
    ...
</beans>
  ]]></programlisting> In many of the examples you will see (and in the sample) applications, we
            will often use "security" as the default namespace rather than "beans", which means we
            can omit the prefix on all the security namespace elements, making the content easier to
            read. You may also want to do this if you have your application context divided up into
            separate files and have most of your security configuration in one of them. Your
            security application context file would then start like this <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<beans:beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/security"
  xmlns:beans="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/security
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/security/spring-security.xsd">
    ...
</beans:beans>
]]></programlisting> We'll assume this syntax is being used from now on in this chapter. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Design of the Namespace</title>
            <para> The namespace is designed to capture the most common uses of the framework and
                provide a simplified and concise syntax for enabling them within an application. The
                design is based around the large-scale dependencies within the framework, and can be
                divided up into the following areas: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>Web/HTTP Security</emphasis> - the most complex part. Sets up
                        the filters and related service beans used to apply the framework
                        authentication mechanisms, to secure URLs, render login and error pages and
                        much more.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>Business Object (Method) Security</emphasis> - options for
                        securing the service layer.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>AuthenticationManager</emphasis> - handles authentication
                        requests from other parts of the framework.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>AccessDecisionManager</emphasis> - provides access decisions
                        for web and method security. A default one will be registered, but you can
                        also choose to use a custom one, declared using normal Spring bean
                        syntax.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>AuthenticationProvider</emphasis>s - mechanisms against which
                        the authentication manager authenticates users. The namespace provides
                        supports for several standard options and also a means of adding custom
                        beans declared using a traditional syntax. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> <emphasis>UserDetailsService</emphasis> - closely related to
                        authentication providers, but often also required by other beans.</para>
                </listitem>
                <!-- todo: diagram and link to other sections which describe the interfaces -->
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>We'll see how to configure these in the following sections.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ns-getting-started">
        <title>Getting Started with Security Namespace Configuration</title>
        <para> In this section, we'll look at how you can build up a namespace configuration to use
            some of the main features of the framework. Let's assume you initially want to get up
            and running as quickly as possible and add authentication support and access control to
            an existing web application, with a few test logins. Then we'll look at how to change
            over to authenticating against a database or other security repository. In later
            sections we'll introduce more advanced namespace configuration options. </para>
        <section xml:id="ns-web-xml">
            <title><literal>web.xml</literal> Configuration</title>
            <para> The first thing you need to do is add the following filter declaration to your
                <literal>web.xml</literal> file: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<filter>
  <filter-name>springSecurityFilterChain</filter-name>
  <filter-class>org.springframework.web.filter.DelegatingFilterProxy</filter-class>
</filter>

<filter-mapping>
  <filter-name>springSecurityFilterChain</filter-name>
  <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern>
</filter-mapping>]]>
      </programlisting> This provides a hook into the Spring Security web
                infrastructure. <classname>DelegatingFilterProxy</classname> is a Spring Framework
                class which delegates to a filter implementation which is defined as a Spring bean
                in your application context. In this case, the bean is named
                <quote>springSecurityFilterChain</quote>, which is an internal infrastructure bean
                created by the namespace to handle web security. Note that you should not use this
                bean name yourself. Once you've added this to your <filename>web.xml</filename>,
                you're ready to start editing your application context file. Web security services
                are configured using the <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> element. </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-minimal">
            <title>A Minimal <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> Configuration</title>
            <para> All you need to enable web security to begin with is <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
    <form-login />
    <logout />
  </http>
  ]]>
</programlisting> Which says that we want all URLs within our application to be secured,
                requiring the role <literal>ROLE_USER</literal> to access them, we want to log in to
                the application using a form with username and password, and that we want a logout URL
                registered which will allow us to log out of the application.
                <literal>&lt;http></literal> element is the parent for all web-related namespace
                functionality. The <literal>&lt;intercept-url></literal> element defines a
                <literal>pattern</literal> which is matched against the URLs of incoming requests
                using an ant path style syntax<footnote>
                <para>See the section on <link xlink:href="#request-matching">Request
                    Matching</link> in the Web Application Infrastructure chapter for more details
                    on how matches are actually performed.</para>
                </footnote>. You can also use regular-expression matching as an alternative (see the
                namespace appendix for more details). The <literal>access</literal> attribute
                defines the access requirements for requests matching the given pattern. With the
                default configuration, this is typically a comma-separated list of roles, one of
                which a user must have to be allowed to make the request. The prefix
                <quote>ROLE_</quote> is a marker which indicates that a simple comparison with the
                user's authorities should be made. In other words, a normal role-based check should
                be used. Access-control in Spring Security is not limited to the use of simple roles
                (hence the use of the prefix to differentiate between different types of security
                attributes). We'll see later how the interpretation can vary<footnote>
                <para>The interpretation of the comma-separated values in the
                    <literal>access</literal> attribute depends on the implementation of the <link
                    xlink:href="#ns-access-manager">AccessDecisionManager</link> which is used. In
                    Spring Security 3.0, the attribute can also be populated with an <link
                    xlink:href="#el-access">EL expression</link>.</para>
                </footnote>.</para>
            <note>
                <para>You can use multiple <literal>&lt;intercept-url&gt;</literal> elements to
                    define different access requirements for different sets of URLs, but they will
                    be evaluated in the order listed and the first match will be used. So you must
                    put the most specific matches at the top. You can also add a
                    <literal>method</literal> attribute to limit the match to a particular HTTP
                    method (<literal>GET</literal>, <literal>POST</literal>, <literal>PUT</literal>
                    etc.). If a request matches multiple patterns, the method-specific match will
                    take precedence regardless of ordering.</para>
            </note>
            <para> To add some users, you can define a set of test data directly in the namespace: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider>
      <user-service>
        <user name="jimi" password="jimispassword" authorities="ROLE_USER, ROLE_ADMIN" />
        <user name="bob" password="bobspassword" authorities="ROLE_USER" />
      </user-service>
    </authentication-provider>
  </authentication-manager>
  ]]>
        </programlisting></para>
            <sidebar>
                <para>If you are familiar with pre-namespace versions of the framework, you can
                    probably already guess roughly what's going on here. The
                    <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> element is responsible for creating a
                    <classname>FilterChainProxy</classname> and the filter beans which it uses.
                    Common problems like incorrect filter ordering are no longer an issue as the
                    filter positions are predefined.</para>
                <para>The <literal>&lt;authentication-provider&gt;</literal> element creates a
                    <classname>DaoAuthenticationProvider</classname> bean and the
                    <literal>&lt;user-service&gt;</literal> element creates an
                    <classname>InMemoryDaoImpl</classname>. All
                    <literal>authentication-provider</literal> elements must be children of the
                    <literal>&lt;authentication-manager></literal> element, which creates a
                    <classname>ProviderManager</classname> and registers the authentication
                    providers with it. You can find more detailed information on the beans that are
                    created in the <link xlink:href="#appendix-namespace">namespace appendix</link>.
                    It's worth cross-checking this if you want to start understanding what the
                    important classes in the framework are and how they are used, particularly if
                    you want to customise things later.</para>
            </sidebar>
            <para> The configuration above defines two users, their passwords and their roles within
                the application (which will be used for access control). It is also possible to load
                user information from a standard properties file using the
                <literal>properties</literal> attribute on <literal>user-service</literal>. See the
                section on <link xlink:href="#core-services-in-memory-service">in-memory
                authentication</link> for more details on the file format. Using the
                <literal>&lt;authentication-provider&gt;</literal> element means that the user
                information will be used by the authentication manager to process authentication
                requests. You can have multiple <literal>&lt;authentication-provider&gt;</literal>
                elements to define different authentication sources and each will be consulted in
                turn.</para>
            <para> At this point you should be able to start up your application and you will be
                required to log in to proceed. Try it out, or try experimenting with the
                <quote>tutorial</quote> sample application that comes with the project.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-form-and-basic">
            <title>Form and Basic Login Options</title>
            <para> You might be wondering where the login form came from when you were prompted to
                log in, since we made no mention of any HTML files or JSPs. In fact, since we didn't
                explicitly set a URL for the login page, Spring Security generates one
                automatically, based on the features that are enabled and using standard values for
                the URL which processes the submitted login, the default target URL the user will be
                sent to after logging in and so on. However, the namespace offers plenty of support
                to allow you to customize these options. For example, if you want to supply your own
                login page, you could use: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/login.jsp*" access="IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY"/>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
    <form-login login-page='/login.jsp'/>
  </http>
  ]]>
    </programlisting> Also note
                that we've added an extra <literal>intercept-url</literal> element to say that any
                requests for the login page should be available to anonymous users <footnote>
                <para>See the chapter on <link xlink:href="#anonymous">anonymous
                    authentication</link> and also the <link xlink:href="#authz-authenticated-voter"
                    >AuthenticatedVoter</link> class for more details on how the value
                    <literal>IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY</literal> is processed.</para>
                </footnote>. Otherwise the request would be matched by the pattern
                <literal>/**</literal> and it wouldn't be possible to access the login page itself!
                This is a common configuration error and will result in an infinite loop in the
                application. Spring Security will emit a warning in the log if your login page
                appears to be secured. It is also possible to have all requests matching a
                particular pattern bypass the security filter chain completely, by defining a
                separate <literal>http</literal> element for the pattern like this: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http pattern="/css/**" security="none"/>
  <http pattern="/login.jsp*" security="none"/>

  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
    <form-login login-page='/login.jsp'/>
  </http>
  ]]>
                </programlisting> From Spring Security 3.1 it is now possible to use multiple
                <literal>http</literal> elements to define separate security filter chain
                configurations for different request patterns. If the <literal>pattern</literal>
                attribute is omitted from an <literal>http</literal> element, it matches all
                requests. Creating an unsecured pattern is a simple example of this syntax, where
                the pattern is mapped to an empty filter chain <footnote>
                <para>The use of multiple <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> elements is an important
                    feature, allowing the namespace to simultaneously support both stateful and
                    stateless paths within the same application, for example. The previous syntax,
                    using the attribute <literal>filters="none"</literal> on an
                    <literal>intercept-url</literal> element is incompatible with this change and is
                    no longer supported in 3.1.</para>
                </footnote>. We'll look at this new syntax in more detail in the chapter on the
                <link xlink:href="#filter-chains-with-ns">Security Filter Chain</link>. </para>
            <para> It's important to realise that these unsecured requests will be completely
                oblivious to any Spring Security web-related configuration or additional attributes
                such as <literal>requires-channel</literal>, so you will not be able to access
                information on the current user or call secured methods during the request. Use
                <literal>access='IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY'</literal> as an alternative if you
                still want the security filter chain to be applied.</para>
            <para>If you want to use basic authentication instead of form login, then change the
                configuration to <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
    <http-basic />
  </http>
  ]]>
    </programlisting> Basic authentication will then take precedence and will be used to
                prompt for a login when a user attempts to access a protected resource. Form login
                is still available in this configuration if you wish to use it, for example through
                a login form embedded in another web page. </para>
            <section xml:id="ns-form-target">
                <title>Setting a Default Post-Login Destination</title>
                <para> If a form login isn't prompted by an attempt to access a protected resource,
                    the <literal>default-target-url</literal> option comes into play. This is the
                    URL the user will be taken to after successfully logging in, and defaults to
                    "/". You can also configure things so that the user <emphasis>always</emphasis>
                    ends up at this page (regardless of whether the login was "on-demand" or they
                    explicitly chose to log in) by setting the
                    <literal>always-use-default-target</literal> attribute to "true". This is useful
                    if your application always requires that the user starts at a "home" page, for
                    example: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http pattern="/login.htm*" security="none"/>
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern='/**' access='ROLE_USER' />
    <form-login login-page='/login.htm' default-target-url='/home.htm'
            always-use-default-target='true' />
  </http>
  ]]>         </programlisting></para>
                <para>For even more control over the destination, you can use the
                    <literal>authentication-success-handler-ref</literal> attribute as an
                    alternative to <literal>default-target-url</literal>. The referenced bean should
                    be an instance of <interfacename>AuthenticationSuccessHandler</interfacename>.
                    You'll find more on this in the <link xlink:href="#form-login-flow-handling"
                    >Core Filters</link> chapter and also in the namespace appendix, as well as
                    information on how to customize the flow when authentication fails. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-logout">
            <title>Logout Handling</title>
            <para>The <literal>logout</literal> element adds support for logging out by navigating
                to a particular URL. The default logout URL is <literal>/j_spring_security_logout</literal>,
                but you can set it to something else using the <literal>logout-url</literal> attribute.
                More information on other available attributes may be found in the namespace appendix.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-auth-providers">
            <title>Using other Authentication Providers</title>
            <para> In practice you will need a more scalable source of user information than a few
                names added to the application context file. Most likely you will want to store your
                user information in something like a database or an LDAP server. LDAP namespace
                configuration is dealt with in the <link xlink:href="#ldap">LDAP chapter</link>, so
                we won't cover it here. If you have a custom implementation of Spring Security's
                <classname>UserDetailsService</classname>, called "myUserDetailsService" in your
                application context, then you can authenticate against this using <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider user-service-ref='myUserDetailsService'/>
  </authentication-manager>
  ]]>
        </programlisting> If you want to use a database, then you can use <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider>
      <jdbc-user-service data-source-ref="securityDataSource"/>
    </authentication-provider>
  </authentication-manager>
  ]]>
        </programlisting> Where <quote>securityDataSource</quote> is the name of a
                <classname>DataSource</classname> bean in the application context, pointing at a
                database containing the standard Spring Security <link
                xlink:href="#db_schema_users_authorities">user data tables</link>. Alternatively,
                you could configure a Spring Security <classname>JdbcDaoImpl</classname> bean and
                point at that using the <literal>user-service-ref</literal> attribute: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider user-service-ref='myUserDetailsService'/>
  </authentication-manager>

  <beans:bean id="myUserDetailsService"
      class="org.springframework.security.core.userdetails.jdbc.JdbcDaoImpl">
    <beans:property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource"/>
  </beans:bean>
  ]]>
        </programlisting> You can also use standard
                <interfacename>AuthenticationProvider</interfacename> beans as follows <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider ref='myAuthenticationProvider'/>
  </authentication-manager>
  ]]>
        </programlisting> where <literal>myAuthenticationProvider</literal> is the name of a
                bean in your application context which implements
                <interfacename>AuthenticationProvider</interfacename>. You can use multiple
                <literal>authentication-provider</literal> elements, in which case the providers
                will be queried in the order they are declared. See <xref linkend="ns-auth-manager"
                /> for more on information on how the Spring Security
                <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename> is configured using the
                namespace. </para>
            <section xml:id="ns-password-encoder">
                <title>Adding a Password Encoder</title>
                <para> Passwords should always be encoded using a secure hashing algorithm designed for the purpose
                    (not a standard algorithm like SHA or MD5). This is supported by the
                    <literal>&lt;password-encoder&gt;</literal> element. With bcrypt
                    encoded passwords, the original authentication provider configuration would look
                    like this: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<beans:bean name="bcryptEncoder" class="org.springframework.security.crypto.bcrypt.BCryptPasswordEncoder"/>

<authentication-manager>
  <authentication-provider>
    <password-encoder ref="bcryptEncoder"/>
    <user-service>
      <user name="jimi" password="d7e6351eaa13189a5a3641bab846c8e8c69ba39f"
            authorities="ROLE_USER, ROLE_ADMIN" />
      <user name="bob" password="4e7421b1b8765d8f9406d87e7cc6aa784c4ab97f"
            authorities="ROLE_USER" />
    </user-service>
  </authentication-provider>
</authentication-manager>
  ]]>
          </programlisting></para>
                <para>Bcrypt is a good choice for most cases, unless you have a legacy system which forces
                    you to use a different algorithm. If you are using a simple hashing algorithm or, even worse,
                    storing plain text passwords, then you should consider migrating to a more secure option like bcrypt.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ns-web-advanced">
        <title>Advanced Web Features</title>
        <section xml:id="ns-remember-me">
            <title>Remember-Me Authentication</title>
            <para>See the separate <link xlink:href="#remember-me">Remember-Me chapter</link> for
                information on remember-me namespace configuration.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-requires-channel">
            <title>Adding HTTP/HTTPS Channel Security</title>
            <para>If your application supports both HTTP and HTTPS, and you require that particular
                URLs can only be accessed over HTTPS, then this is directly supported using the
                <literal>requires-channel</literal> attribute on
                <literal>&lt;intercept-url&gt;</literal>: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/secure/**" access="ROLE_USER" requires-channel="https"/>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" requires-channel="any"/>
    ...
  </http>]]>
        </programlisting>With this configuration in place, if a user attempts to access
                anything matching the "/secure/**" pattern using HTTP, they will first be redirected
                to an HTTPS URL
                <footnote><para>For more details on how channel-processing is implemented, see the Javadoc
                 for <classname>ChannelProcessingFilter</classname> and related classes.
                </para></footnote>.
                The available options are "http", "https" or "any". Using the value
                "any" means that either HTTP or HTTPS can be used. </para>
            <para>If your application uses non-standard ports for HTTP and/or HTTPS, you can specify
                a list of port mappings as follows: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    ...
    <port-mappings>
      <port-mapping http="9080" https="9443"/>
    </port-mappings>
  </http>]]>
                </programlisting>
                Note that in order to be truly secure, an application should not use HTTP at all or switch
                between HTTP and HTTPS. It should start in HTTPS (with the user entering an HTTPS URL) and
                use a secure connection throughout to avoid any possibility of man-in-the-middle attacks.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-session-mgmt">
            <title>Session Management</title>
            <section>
                <title>Detecting Timeouts</title>
                <para> You can configure Spring Security to detect the submission of an invalid
                    session ID and redirect the user to an appropriate URL. This is achieved through
                    the <literal>session-management</literal> element: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    ...
    <session-management invalid-session-url="/invalidSession.htm" />
    </http>]]></programlisting>Note that if you use this mechanism to detect session timeouts, it
                    may falsely report an error if the user logs out and then logs back in without
                    closing the browser. This is because the session cookie is not cleared when you
                    invalidate the session and will be resubmitted even if the user has logged out.
                    You may be able to explicitly delete the JSESSIONID cookie on logging out, for
                    example by using the following syntax in the logout handler: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <logout delete-cookies="JSESSIONID" />
  </http>
  ]]></programlisting> Unfortunately this can't be guaranteed to work with every servlet container,
                    so you will need to test it in your environment<footnote>
                    <para>If you are running your application behind a proxy, you may also be able
                        to remove the session cookie by configuring the proxy server. For example,
                        using Apache HTTPD's mod_headers, the following directive would delete the
                        <literal>JSESSIONID</literal> cookie by expiring it in the response to a
                        logout request (assuming the application is deployed under the path
                        <literal>/tutorial</literal>):
                        <programlisting language="xml"> &lt;LocationMatch "/tutorial/j_spring_security_logout">
  Header always set Set-Cookie "JSESSIONID=;Path=/tutorial;Expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 GMT"
 &lt;/LocationMatch></programlisting></para>
                    </footnote>. </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="ns-concurrent-sessions">
                <title>Concurrent Session Control</title>
                <para>If you wish to place constraints on a single user's ability to log in to your
                    application, Spring Security supports this out of the box with the following
                    simple additions. First you need to add the following listener to your
                    <filename>web.xml</filename> file to keep Spring Security updated about session
                    lifecycle events: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <listener>
    <listener-class>
      org.springframework.security.web.session.HttpSessionEventPublisher
    </listener-class>
  </listener>
]]></programlisting> Then add the following lines to your application context: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    ...
    <session-management>
        <concurrency-control max-sessions="1" />
    </session-management>
  </http>]]>
        </programlisting> This will prevent a user from logging in multiple times - a
                    second login will cause the first to be invalidated. Often you would prefer to
                    prevent a second login, in which case you can use <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    ...
    <session-management>
        <concurrency-control max-sessions="1" error-if-maximum-exceeded="true" />
    </session-management>
  </http>]]>
        </programlisting>The second login will then be rejected. By
                    <quote>rejected</quote>, we mean that the user will be sent to the
                    <literal>authentication-failure-url</literal> if form-based login is being used.
                    If the second authentication takes place through another non-interactive
                    mechanism, such as <quote>remember-me</quote>, an <quote>unauthorized</quote>
                    (402) error will be sent to the client. If instead you want to use an error
                    page, you can add the attribute
                    <literal>session-authentication-error-url</literal> to the
                    <literal>session-management</literal> element. </para>
                <para>If you are using a customized authentication filter for form-based login, then
                    you have to configure concurrent session control support explicitly. More
                    details can be found in the <link xlink:href="#session-mgmt">Session Management
                    chapter</link>. </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="ns-session-fixation">
                <title>Session Fixation Attack Protection</title>
                <para> <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Session_fixation">Session
                    fixation</link> attacks are a potential risk where it is possible for a
                    malicious attacker to create a session by accessing a site, then persuade
                    another user to log in with the same session (by sending them a link containing
                    the session identifier as a parameter, for example). Spring Security protects
                    against this automatically by creating a new session when a user logs in. If you
                    don't require this protection, or it conflicts with some other requirement, you
                    can control the behaviour using the
                    <literal>session-fixation-protection</literal> attribute on
                    <literal>&lt;session-management&gt;</literal>, which has three options <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>migrateSession</literal> - creates a new session and copies
                            the existing session attributes to the new session. This is the
                            default.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>none</literal> - Don't do anything. The original session will
                            be retained.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><literal>newSession</literal> - Create a new "clean" session, without
                            copying the existing session data.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    See the <link xlink:href="#session-mgmt">Session Management</link> chapter for
                    additional information.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-openid">
            <title>OpenID Support</title>
            <para>The namespace supports <link xlink:href="http://openid.net/">OpenID</link> login
                either instead of, or in addition to normal form-based login, with a simple change: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
    <intercept-url pattern="/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
    <openid-login />
  </http>
]]></programlisting>You should then register yourself with an OpenID provider (such as
                myopenid.com), and add the user information to your in-memory
                <literal>&lt;user-service&gt;</literal> : <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <user name="http://jimi.hendrix.myopenid.com/" authorities="ROLE_USER" />
]]></programlisting> You should be able to login using the <literal>myopenid.com</literal> site to
                authenticate. It is also possible to select a specific
                <interfacename>UserDetailsService</interfacename> bean for use OpenID by setting the
                <literal>user-service-ref</literal> attribute on the <literal>openid-login</literal>
                element. See the previous section on <link xlink:href="#ns-auth-providers"
                >authentication providers</link> for more information. Note that we have omitted the
                password attribute from the above user configuration, since this set of user data is
                only being used to load the authorities for the user. A random password will be
                generate internally, preventing you from accidentally using this user data as an
                authentication source elsewhere in your configuration.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Attribute Exchange</title>
                <para>Support for OpenID <link
                    xlink:href="http://openid.net/specs/openid-attribute-exchange-1_0.html"
                    >attribute exchange</link>. As an example, the following configuration would
                    attempt to retrieve the email and full name from the OpenID provider, for use by
                    the application:<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
 <openid-login>
  <attribute-exchange>
    <openid-attribute name="email" type="http://axschema.org/contact/email" required="true"/>
    <openid-attribute name="name" type="http://axschema.org/namePerson"/>
  </attribute-exchange>
 </openid-login>]]></programlisting>The <quote>type</quote> of each OpenID attribute is a URI,
                    determined by a particular schema, in this case <link
                    xlink:href="http://axschema.org/">http://axschema.org/</link>. If an attribute
                    must be retrieved for successful authentication, the <literal>required</literal>
                    attribute can be set. The exact schema and attributes supported will depend on
                    your OpenID provider. The attribute values are returned as part of the
                    authentication process and can be accessed afterwards using the following code:
                    <programlisting language="java">
OpenIDAuthenticationToken token =
    (OpenIDAuthenticationToken)SecurityContextHolder.getContext().getAuthentication();
List&lt;OpenIDAttribute> attributes = token.getAttributes();</programlisting>The
                    <classname>OpenIDAttribute</classname> contains the attribute type and the
                    retrieved value (or values in the case of multi-valued attributes). We'll see
                    more about how the <classname>SecurityContextHolder</classname> class is used
                    when we look at core Spring Security components in the <link
                    xlink:href="#core-components">technical overview</link> chapter. Multiple
                    attribute exchange configurations are also be supported, if you wish to use
                    multiple identity providers. You can supply multiple
                    <literal>attribute-exchange</literal> elements, using an
                    <literal>identifier-matcher</literal> attribute on each. This contains a regular
                    expression which will be matched against the OpenID identifier supplied by the
                    user. See the OpenID sample application in the codebase for an example
                    configuration, providing different attribute lists for the Google, Yahoo and
                    MyOpenID providers.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-headers">
            <title>Response Headers</title>
            <para>A lot of different attacks to hijack content, sessions or connections are available and lately
                browsers (optionally) can help to prevent those attacks. To enable these features we need to send some
                additional headers to the client. Spring Security allows for easy configuration for several headers.
                <progamlisting language="xml">
                    <![CDATA[
                            <headers/>
                    ]]>
                </progamlisting>
            </para>
            <para>Specifying the single headers element adds all the explicitly supported headers
                with their default settings. If you only want select headers to be added,
                you can add one or more of the child elements as shown below.
                <progamlisting language="xml">
                    <![CDATA[
                            <headers>
                                <!-- Add Cache-Control and Pragma headers -->
                                <cache-control/>
                                <!-- Add X-Content-Type-Options with value of nosniff -->
                                <content-type-options/>
                                <!-- Add custom headers -->
                                <header name="foo" value="bar"/>
                                <-- Adds HTTP Strict Transport Security (HSTS) for secure requests -->
                                <hsts/>
                                <!-- Add X-Frame-Options with a value of DENY -->
                                <frame-options/>
                                <!-- Adds X-XSS-Protection with value of 1; mode=block-->
                                <xss-protection/>
                            </headers>
                    ]]>
                </progamlisting>
            </para>
            <para>For additional information on how to customize the headers element refer to the <link xlink:href="nsa-headers">headers</link>
                section of the Security Namespace appendix.</para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="ns-custom-filters">
            <title>Adding in Your Own Filters</title>
            <para>If you've used Spring Security before, you'll know that the framework maintains a
                chain of filters in order to apply its services. You may want to add your own
                filters to the stack at particular locations or use a Spring Security filter for
                which there isn't currently a namespace configuration option (CAS, for example). Or
                you might want to use a customized version of a standard namespace filter, such as
                the <classname>UsernamePasswordAuthenticationFilter</classname> which is created by the
                <literal>&lt;form-login&gt;</literal> element, taking advantage of some of the extra
                configuration options which are available by using the bean explicitly. How can you
                do this with namespace configuration, since the filter chain is not directly
                exposed? </para>
            <para>The order of the filters is always strictly enforced when using the namespace.
                When the application context is being created, the filter beans are sorted by the
                namespace handling code and the standard Spring Security filters each have an alias
                in the namespace and a well-known position.<note>
                <para>In previous versions, the sorting took place after the filter instances had
                    been created, during post-processing of the application context. In version 3.0+
                    the sorting is now done at the bean metadata level, before the classes have been
                    instantiated. This has implications for how you add your own filters to the
                    stack as the entire filter list must be known during the parsing of the
                    <literal>&lt;http></literal> element, so the syntax has changed slightly in
                    3.0.</para>
                </note>The filters, aliases and namespace elements/attributes which create the
                filters are shown in <xref linkend="filter-stack"/>. The filters are listed in the
                order in which they occur in the filter chain. <table xml:id="filter-stack">
                <title>Standard Filter Aliases and Ordering</title>
                <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">Alias</entry>
                            <entry align="center">Filter Class</entry>
                            <entry align="center">Namespace Element or Attribute</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry> CHANNEL_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>ChannelProcessingFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/intercept-url@requires-channel</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> SECURITY_CONTEXT_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><classname>SecurityContextPersistenceFilter</classname></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> CONCURRENT_SESSION_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>ConcurrentSessionFilter</literal> </entry>
                            <entry><literal>session-management/concurrency-control</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>HEADERS_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>HeadersFilter</literal> </entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/headers</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> LOGOUT_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>LogoutFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/logout</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> X509_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>X509AuthenticationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/x509</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> PRE_AUTH_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>AstractPreAuthenticatedProcessingFilter</literal>
                                Subclasses</entry>
                            <entry>N/A</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> CAS_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>CasAuthenticationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry>N/A</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> FORM_LOGIN_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>UsernamePasswordAuthenticationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/form-login</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> BASIC_AUTH_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>BasicAuthenticationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/http-basic</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> SERVLET_API_SUPPORT_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>SecurityContextHolderAwareRequestFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/@servlet-api-provision</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>JAAS_API_SUPPORT_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>JaasApiIntegrationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/@jaas-api-provision</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> REMEMBER_ME_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><classname>RememberMeAuthenticationFilter</classname></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/remember-me</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> ANONYMOUS_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>AnonymousAuthenticationFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http/anonymous</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> SESSION_MANAGEMENT_FILTER</entry>
                            <entry><literal>SessionManagementFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry><literal>session-management</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>EXCEPTION_TRANSLATION_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><classname>ExceptionTranslationFilter</classname></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> FILTER_SECURITY_INTERCEPTOR </entry>
                            <entry><classname>FilterSecurityInterceptor</classname></entry>
                            <entry><literal>http</literal></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> SWITCH_USER_FILTER </entry>
                            <entry><literal>SwitchUserFilter</literal></entry>
                            <entry>N/A</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
                </table> You can add your own filter to the stack, using the
                <literal>custom-filter</literal> element and one of these names to specify the
                position your filter should appear at: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http>
     <custom-filter position="FORM_LOGIN_FILTER" ref="myFilter" />
  </http>

  <beans:bean id="myFilter" class="com.mycompany.MySpecialAuthenticationFilter"/>
  ]]>
  </programlisting> You can also use the <literal>after</literal> or <literal>before</literal>
                attributes if you want your filter to be inserted before or after another filter in
                the stack. The names "FIRST" and "LAST" can be used with the
                <literal>position</literal> attribute to indicate that you want your filter to
                appear before or after the entire stack, respectively. </para>
            <tip>
                <title>Avoiding filter position conflicts</title>
                <para> If you are inserting a custom filter which may occupy the same position as
                    one of the standard filters created by the namespace then it's important that
                    you don't include the namespace versions by mistake. Remove any elements which create
                    filters whose functionality you want to replace. </para>
                <para> Note that you can't replace filters which are created by the use of the
                    <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> element itself -
                    <classname>SecurityContextPersistenceFilter</classname>,
                    <classname>ExceptionTranslationFilter</classname> or
                    <classname>FilterSecurityInterceptor</classname>. Some other filters are added
                    by default, but you can disable them. An <classname>AnonymousAuthenticationFilter</classname>
                    is added by default and unless you have
                    <link xlink:href="#ns-session-fixation">session-fixation protection</link>
                    disabled, a <classname>SessionManagementFilter</classname> will also be added
                    to the filter chain.
                </para>
            </tip>
            <para> If you're replacing a namespace filter which requires an authentication entry
                point (i.e. where the authentication process is triggered by an attempt by an
                unauthenticated user to access to a secured resource), you will need to add a custom
                entry point bean too. </para>
            <section xml:id="ns-entry-point-ref">
                <title>Setting a Custom
                    <interfacename>AuthenticationEntryPoint</interfacename></title>
                <para> If you aren't using form login, OpenID or basic authentication through the
                    namespace, you may want to define an authentication filter and entry point using
                    a traditional bean syntax and link them into the namespace, as we've just seen.
                    The corresponding <interfacename>AuthenticationEntryPoint</interfacename> can be
                    set using the <literal>entry-point-ref</literal> attribute on the
                    <literal>&lt;http&gt;</literal> element. </para>
                <para> The CAS sample application is a good example of the use of custom beans with
                    the namespace, including this syntax. If you aren't familiar with authentication
                    entry points, they are discussed in the <link
                    xlink:href="#tech-intro-auth-entry-point">technical overview</link> chapter.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ns-method-security">
        <title>Method Security</title>
        <para>From version 2.0 onwards Spring Security has improved support substantially for adding
            security to your service layer methods. It provides support for JSR-250 annotation
            security as well as the framework's original <literal>@Secured</literal> annotation.
            From 3.0 you can also make use of new <link xlink:href="#el-access">expression-based
            annotations</link>. You can apply security to a single bean, using the
            <literal>intercept-methods</literal> element to decorate the bean declaration, or you
            can secure multiple beans across the entire service layer using the AspectJ style
            pointcuts. </para>
        <section xml:id="ns-global-method">
            <title>The <literal>&lt;global-method-security&gt;</literal> Element</title>
            <para> This element is used to enable annotation-based security in your application (by
                setting the appropriate attributes on the element), and also to group together
                security pointcut declarations which will be applied across your entire application
                context. You should only declare one
                <literal>&lt;global-method-security&gt;</literal> element. The following declaration
                would enable support for Spring Security's <literal>@Secured</literal>: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <global-method-security secured-annotations="enabled" />
  ]]>
</programlisting> Adding an annotation to a method (on an class or interface) would then limit
                the access to that method accordingly. Spring Security's native annotation support
                defines a set of attributes for the method. These will be passed to the
                <interfacename>AccessDecisionManager</interfacename> for it to make the actual
                decision:
                <programlisting language="java">
  public interface BankService {

    @Secured("IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY")
    public Account readAccount(Long id);

    @Secured("IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY")
    public Account[] findAccounts();

    @Secured("ROLE_TELLER")
    public Account post(Account account, double amount);
  }
</programlisting>Support
                for JSR-250 annotations can be enabled using <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <global-method-security jsr250-annotations="enabled" />
  ]]>
        </programlisting>These are standards-based and allow simple role-based constraints to
                be applied but do not have the power Spring Security's native annotations. To use
                the new expression-based syntax, you would use <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <global-method-security pre-post-annotations="enabled" />
  ]]></programlisting>and the equivalent Java code would
                be<programlisting language="java">
   public interface BankService {

     @PreAuthorize("isAnonymous()")
     public Account readAccount(Long id);

     @PreAuthorize("isAnonymous()")
     public Account[] findAccounts();

     @PreAuthorize("hasAuthority('ROLE_TELLER')")
     public Account post(Account account, double amount);
   }
        </programlisting>Expression-based
                annotations are a good choice if you need to define simple rules that go beyond
                checking the role names against the user's list of authorities. <note>
                <para>The annotated methods will only be secured for instances which are defined as
                    Spring beans (in the same application context in which method-security is
                    enabled). If you want to secure instances which are not created by Spring (using
                    the <literal>new</literal> operator, for example) then you need to use AspectJ.
                </para>
            </note>
                <note>
                    <para>
                    You can enable more than one type of annotation in the same application, but
                    only one type should be used for any interface or class as the behaviour will not
                    be well-defined otherwise. If two annotations are found which apply to a particular
                    method, then only one of them will be applied.
                </para>
                </note> </para>
            <section xml:id="ns-protect-pointcut">
                <title>Adding Security Pointcuts using <literal>protect-pointcut</literal></title>
                <para> The use of <literal>protect-pointcut</literal> is particularly powerful, as
                    it allows you to apply security to many beans with only a simple declaration.
                    Consider the following example: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <global-method-security>
    <protect-pointcut expression="execution(* com.mycompany.*Service.*(..))"
         access="ROLE_USER"/>
  </global-method-security>
]]>
          </programlisting> This will protect all methods on beans declared in the application
                    context whose classes are in the <literal>com.mycompany</literal> package and
                    whose class names end in "Service". Only users with the
                    <literal>ROLE_USER</literal> role will be able to invoke these methods. As with
                    URL matching, the most specific matches must come first in the list of
                    pointcuts, as the first matching expression will be used. Security
                    annotations take precedence over pointcuts.
                    </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ns-access-manager">
        <title>The Default AccessDecisionManager</title>
        <para> This section assumes you have some knowledge of the underlying architecture for
            access-control within Spring Security. If you don't you can skip it and come back to it
            later, as this section is only really relevant for people who need to do some
            customization in order to use more than simple role-based security. </para>
        <para> When you use a namespace configuration, a default instance of
            <interfacename>AccessDecisionManager</interfacename> is automatically registered for you
            and will be used for making access decisions for method invocations and web URL access,
            based on the access attributes you specify in your <literal>intercept-url</literal> and
            <literal>protect-pointcut</literal> declarations (and in annotations if you are using
            annotation secured methods). </para>
        <para> The default strategy is to use an <classname>AffirmativeBased</classname>
            <interfacename>AccessDecisionManager</interfacename> with a
            <classname>RoleVoter</classname> and an <classname>AuthenticatedVoter</classname>. You
            can find out more about these in the chapter on <link xlink:href="#authz-arch"
            >authorization</link>.</para>
        <section xml:id="ns-custom-access-mgr">
            <title>Customizing the AccessDecisionManager</title>
            <para> If you need to use a more complicated access control strategy then it is easy to
                set an alternative for both method and web security. </para>
            <para> For method security, you do this by setting the
                <literal>access-decision-manager-ref</literal> attribute on
                <literal>global-method-security</literal> to the <literal>id</literal> of the appropriate
                <interfacename>AccessDecisionManager</interfacename> bean in the application
                context: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <global-method-security access-decision-manager-ref="myAccessDecisionManagerBean">
    ...
  </global-method-security>
  ]]></programlisting></para>
            <para> The syntax for web security is the same, but on the <literal>http</literal>
                element: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <http access-decision-manager-ref="myAccessDecisionManagerBean">
    ...
  </http>
  ]]></programlisting></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ns-auth-manager">
        <title>The Authentication Manager and the Namespace</title>
        <para> The main interface which provides authentication services in Spring Security is the
            <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename>. This is usually an instance of
            Spring Security's <classname>ProviderManager</classname> class, which you may already be
            familiar with if you've used the framework before. If not, it will be covered later, in
            the <link xlink:href="#tech-intro-authentication">technical overview chapter</link>. The
            bean instance is registered using the <literal>authentication-manager</literal>
            namespace element. You can't use a custom <classname>AuthenticationManager</classname>
            if you are using either HTTP or method security through the namespace, but this should
            not be a problem as you have full control over the
            <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>s that are used.</para>
        <para> You may want to register additional <classname>AuthenticationProvider</classname>
            beans with the <classname>ProviderManager</classname> and you can do this using the
            <literal>&lt;authentication-provider&gt;</literal> element with the
            <literal>ref</literal> attribute, where the value of the attribute is the name of the
            provider bean you want to add. For example: <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <authentication-manager>
    <authentication-provider ref="casAuthenticationProvider"/>
  </authentication-manager>

  <bean id="casAuthenticationProvider"
      class="org.springframework.security.cas.authentication.CasAuthenticationProvider">
    ...
  </bean>
  ]]></programlisting></para>
        <para> Another common requirement is that another bean in the context may require a
            reference to the <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename>. You can easily
            register an alias for the <interfacename>AuthenticationManager</interfacename> and use
            this name elsewhere in your application context. <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
  <security:authentication-manager alias="authenticationManager">
     ...
  </security:authentication-manager>

  <bean id="customizedFormLoginFilter"
        class="com.somecompany.security.web.CustomFormLoginFilter">
     <property name="authenticationManager" ref="authenticationManager"/>
     ...
  </bean>
  ]]></programlisting></para>
    </section>
</chapter>
