<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    version="5.0" xml:id="sample-apps">
    <info>
        <title xml:id="samples">Sample Applications</title>
    </info>
    <para> There are several sample web applications that are available with the project. To avoid
        an overly large download, only the "tutorial" and "contacts" samples are included in the
        distribution zip file. You can either build the others yourself, or you can obtain the war
        files individually from the central Maven repository. We'd recommend the former. You can get
        the source as described in <link xlink:href="#get-source">the introduction</link> and it's
        easy to build the project yourself. There's more information on the project web site at
        <link xlink:href="http://www.springsource.org/security/">
        http://www.springsource.org/security/ </link>. All paths referred to in this
        chapter are relative to the project source directory. </para>
    <section xml:id="tutorial-sample">
        <title>Tutorial Sample</title>
        <para> The tutorial sample is a nice basic example to get you started. It uses simple
            namespace configuration throughout. The compiled application is included in the
            distribution zip file, ready to be deployed into your web container
            (<filename>spring-security-samples-tutorial-3.1.x.war</filename>). The <link
            xlink:href="#ns-form-and-basic">form-based</link> authentication mechanism is used in
            combination with the commonly-used <link xlink:href="#remember-me">remember-me</link>
            authentication provider to automatically remember the login using cookies.</para>
        <para>We recommend you start with the tutorial sample, as the XML is minimal and easy to
            follow. Most importantly, you can easily add this one XML file (and its corresponding
            <literal>web.xml</literal> entries) to your existing application. Only when this basic
            integration is achieved do we suggest you attempt adding in method authorization or
            domain object security.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="contacts-sample">
        <title>Contacts</title>
        <para> The Contacts Sample is an advanced example in that it illustrates the more powerful
            features of domain object access control lists (ACLs) in addition to basic application
            security. The application provides an interface with which the users are able to
            administer a simple database of contacts (the domain objects).</para>
        <para>To deploy, simply copy the WAR file from Spring Security distribution into your
            container’s <literal>webapps</literal> directory. The war should be called
            <filename>spring-security-samples-contacts-3.1.x.war</filename> (the appended version
            number will vary depending on what release you are using). </para>
        <para>After starting your container, check the application can load. Visit
            <literal>http://localhost:8080/contacts</literal> (or whichever URL is appropriate for
            your web container and the WAR you deployed). </para>
        <para>Next, click "Debug". You will be prompted to authenticate, and a series of usernames
            and passwords are suggested on that page. Simply authenticate with any of these and view
            the resulting page. It should contain a success message similar to the following:
            <literallayout>
Security Debug Information

Authentication object is of type:
org.springframework.security.authentication.UsernamePasswordAuthenticationToken

Authentication object as a String:

org.springframework.security.authentication.UsernamePasswordAuthenticationToken@1f127853:
Principal: org.springframework.security.core.userdetails.User@b07ed00: Username: rod; \
Password: [PROTECTED]; Enabled: true; AccountNonExpired: true;
credentialsNonExpired: true; AccountNonLocked: true; \
Granted Authorities: ROLE_SUPERVISOR, ROLE_USER; \
Password: [PROTECTED]; Authenticated: true; \
Details: org.springframework.security.web.authentication.WebAuthenticationDetails@0: \
RemoteIpAddress: 127.0.0.1; SessionId: 8fkp8t83ohar; \
Granted Authorities: ROLE_SUPERVISOR, ROLE_USER

Authentication object holds the following granted authorities:

ROLE_SUPERVISOR (getAuthority(): ROLE_SUPERVISOR)
ROLE_USER (getAuthority(): ROLE_USER)

Success! Your web filters appear to be properly configured!
    </literallayout></para>
        <para>Once you successfully receive the above message, return to the sample application's
            home page and click "Manage". You can then try out the application. Notice that only the
            contacts available to the currently logged on user are displayed, and only users with
            <literal>ROLE_SUPERVISOR</literal> are granted access to delete their contacts. Behind
            the scenes, the <classname>MethodSecurityInterceptor</classname> is securing the
            business objects. </para>
        <para>The application allows you to modify the access control lists associated with
            different contacts. Be sure to give this a try and understand how it works by reviewing
            the application context XML files.</para>
        <!--
    TODO: Reintroduce standalone client example.
    <para>The Contacts sample application also includes a
        <literal>client</literal> directory. Inside you will find a small
        application that queries the backend business objects using several
        web services protocols. This demonstrates how to use Spring Security
        for authentication with Spring remoting protocols. To try this client,
        ensure your servlet container is still running the Contacts sample
        application, and then execute <literal>client rod koala</literal>. The
        command-line parameters respectively represent the username to use,
        and the password to use. Note that you may need to edit
        <literal>client.properties</literal> to use a different target
        URL.</para>
-->
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ldap-sample">
        <title>LDAP Sample</title>
        <para> The LDAP sample application provides a basic configuration and sets up both a
            namespace configuration and an equivalent configuration using traditional beans, both in
            the same application context file. This means there are actually two identical
            authentication providers configured in this application. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="openid-sample">
        <title>OpenID Sample</title>
        <para>
            The OpenID sample demonstrates how to use the namespace to configure OpenID and how to set up
            <link xlink:href="http://openid.net/specs/openid-attribute-exchange-1_0.html">attribute exchange</link>
            configurations for Google, Yahoo and MyOpenID identity providers (you can experiment with adding others
            if you wish). It uses the JQuery-based <link xlink:href="http://code.google.com/p/openid-selector/">openid-selector</link>
            project to provide a user-friendly login page which allows the user to easily select a provider, rather than
            typing in the full OpenID identifier.
        </para>
        <para>
            The application differs from normal authentication scenarios in that it allows any user to access the site (provided
            their OpenID authentication is successful). The first time you login, you will get a <quote>Welcome [your name]"</quote>
            message. If you logout and log back in (with the same OpenID identity) then this should change to <quote>Welcome Back</quote>.
            This is achieved by using a custom <interfacename>UserDetailsService</interfacename> which assigns a standard role
            to any user and stores the identities internally in a map. Obviously a real application would use a database instead.
            Have a look at the source form more information. This class also takes into account the fact that different attributes may be returned
            from different providers and builds the name with which it addresses the user accordingly.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="cas-sample">
        <title>CAS Sample</title>
        <para> The CAS sample requires that you run both a CAS server and CAS client. It isn't
            included in the distribution so you should check out the project code as described in
            <link xlink:href="#get-source">the introduction</link>. You'll find the relevant files
            under the <filename>sample/cas</filename> directory. There's also a
            <filename>Readme.txt</filename> file in there which explains how to run both the server
            and the client directly from the source tree, complete with SSL support. You have to
            download the CAS Server web application (a war file) from the CAS site and drop it into
            the <filename>samples/cas/server</filename> directory. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="preauth-sample">
        <title>Pre-Authentication Sample</title>
        <para> This sample application demonstrates how to wire up beans from the <link
            xlink:href="#preauth">pre-authentication</link> framework to make use of login
            information from a J2EE container. The user name and roles are those setup by the
            container. </para>
        <para> The code is in <filename>samples/preauth</filename>. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
