<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="x509">
    <info><title>X.509 Authentication</title></info>

    <section xml:id="x509-overview"><info><title>Overview</title></info>

        <para>The most common use of X.509 certificate authentication is in verifying the identity
            of a server when using SSL, most commonly when using HTTPS from a browser. The browser
            will automatically check that the certificate presented by a server has been issued (ie
            digitally signed) by one of a list of trusted certificate authorities which it
            maintains.</para>
        <para>You can also use SSL with <quote>mutual authentication</quote>; the server will then
            request a valid certificate from the client as part of the SSL handshake. The server
            will authenticate the client by checking that its certificate is signed by an
            acceptable authority. If a valid certificate has been provided, it can be obtained
            through the servlet API in an application. Spring Security X.509 module extracts the
            certificate using a filter. It maps the certificate to an application user and loads that
            user's set of granted authorities for use with the standard Spring Security infrastructure.</para>
        <para>You should be familiar with using certificates and setting up client authentication
            for your servlet container before attempting to use it with Spring Security. Most of the
            work is in creating and installing suitable certificates and keys. For example, if
            you're using Tomcat then read the instructions here <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-6.0-doc/ssl-howto.html">http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-6.0-doc/ssl-howto.html</uri>. It's important that
            you get this working before trying it out with Spring Security</para>
    </section>
    <section><info><title>Adding X.509 Authentication to Your Web Application</title></info>

        <para> Enabling X.509 client authentication is very straightforward. Just add the <literal>&lt;x509/&gt;</literal> element to your http security namespace configuration. <programlisting>
&lt;http&gt;
 ...
    &lt;x509 subject-principal-regex="CN=(.*?)," user-service-ref="userService"/&gt;
 ...
&lt;/http&gt;
            </programlisting> The element has two optional attributes: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>subject-principal-regex</literal>. The regular expression used to
                        extract a username from the certificate's subject name. The default value is
                        shown above. This is the username which will be passed to the <interfacename>UserDetailsService</interfacename> to load the authorities for the
                    user.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><literal>user-service-ref</literal>. This is the bean Id of the
                            <interfacename>UserDetailsService</interfacename> to be used with X.509.
                        It isn't needed if there is only one defined in your application
                    context.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist> The <literal>subject-principal-regex</literal> should contain a single
            group. For example the default expression "CN=(.*?)," matches the common name field. So
            if the subject name in the certificate is "CN=Jimi Hendrix, OU=...", this will give a
            user name of "Jimi Hendrix". The matches are case insensitive. So "emailAddress=(.?),"
            will match "EMAILADDRESS=jimi@hendrix.org,CN=..." giving a user name "jimi@hendrix.org".
            If the client presents a certificate and a valid username is successfully extracted,
            then there should be a valid <classname>Authentication</classname> object in the
            security context. If no certificate is found, or no corresponding user could be found
            then the security context will remain empty. This means that you can easily use X.509
            authentication with other options such as a form-based login. </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="x509-ssl-config">
        <info><title>Setting up SSL in Tomcat</title></info>

        <para>There are some pre-generated certificates in the
            <filename>samples/certificate</filename> directory in the Spring Security project.
            You can use these to enable SSL for testing if you don't want to generate your own. The file
                <filename>server.jks</filename> contains the server certificate, private key and the
            issuing certificate authority certificate. There are also some client certificate files
            for the users from the sample applications. You can install these in your browser to enable
            SSL client authentication.
        </para>
        <para>
            To run tomcat with SSL support, drop the <filename>server.jks</filename> file into the
            tomcat <filename>conf</filename> directory and add the following connector to the
            <filename>server.xml</filename> file
                <programlisting>
&lt;Connector port="8443" protocol="HTTP/1.1" SSLEnabled="true" scheme="https" secure="true"
            clientAuth="true" sslProtocol="TLS"
            keystoreFile="${catalina.home}/conf/server.jks"
            keystoreType="JKS" keystorePass="password"
            truststoreFile="${catalina.home}/conf/server.jks"
            truststoreType="JKS" truststorePass="password"
/&gt;
                </programlisting>
            <parameter>clientAuth</parameter> can also be set to <parameter>want</parameter> if you still
            want SSL connections to succeed even if the client doesn't provide a certificate.
            Clients which don't present a certificate won't be able to access any objects secured by
            Spring Security unless you use a non-X.509 authentication mechanism, such as form authentication.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>